At this moment
まさにその時
A fierce wind blows
一陣の突風が吹き荒れ
The Taiji Hall plaque
太極殿の扁額が
Is blown down by the wind
風に攫われ
And lands at your feet
汝の足元に落ちたり。
You seize the opportunity
汝は機を逃さず
Lift the plaque
扁額を担ぎ
Climb high and shout
高いところに登り、声を張り上げる。
Heaven's mandate is with me
天命我にあり。
You all
お前ら
Surrender quickly
速やかに帰順せぬか
Kill
かかれ！！
This shout
その一喝
Not only greatly boosts your side's morale
味方の士気は奮い立ち
But also shakes the defenders' resolve
守備軍の動揺を誘いしものなり
Cornered as you are
追い詰められた汝
Fight heroically
勇猛無双にして
Successfully break through
ついに包囲を突破し
And ascend the throne
帝位を手に入れた。
Enthrone the Chen family's eldest daughter as Lady Chen
陳家の長女を「陳夫人」として立て
Change the era name to Tianming
元号を「天命」と改めたり。
Because the throne was gained unjustly
不正にて帝位を得たことを自覚し
You know your sins are grave
その罪の深さを悟ったゆえ
To atone for your wrongs
過ちを償うため
You diligently govern
汝は勤め民の訴えを聞き
Working from dawn to dusk
朝より晩まで政治に精励する。
With the virtuous Empress Xie
“賢后”たる謝氏は
Managing internal affairs
後宮を統べ
And the female chancellor
“女相”たる陳氏は
Lady Chen assisting at your side
側に侍りて輔く。
Talented ministers and brave generals emerge
汝が麾下（きか）には腕利きの臣下にして驍将多く、
With the entire nation's strength
全国の力を挙げて
You advance the northern campaign
北伐を推し進め
Like splitting bamboo
破竹の勢を以て北進する。
In the seventh year of Tianming
天命七年
Sikong Yao personally leads a great army
司空耀は自ら大軍を率いて
To capture Yong'an
永安を襲い取る。
The Wutu
鄔奴は
Had already gathered a hundred thousand
すでに十万の兵を集め
To cut off your retreat
その後路を断さんと待ち構えておったが
Unexpectedly, fire stones fall from heaven
思いもよらぬ天より火石が降り
Landing on the Wutu camp
鄔奴の軍営に落ちぬ。
The Wutu army collapses
これにより、鄔奴の大軍はたちまち潰走せり。
The Wutu general Shi Lang exclaims
鄔奴の大将軍・石狼（せき ろう）は
This is heaven's mandate
「これこそ天命なり！」と呼び叫ぶ
Then
そして
He commits suicide
自刎しぬ。
In the tenth year of Tianming
天命十年
The lost northern territories
北方の失地
Are all recovered
ことごとく回復せし。
Neighboring countries
すべての隣国は
All submit
臣従の礼を取れり。
In the twenty-ninth year of Tianming
天命二十九年
Sikong Yao dies after taking elixirs
司空耀は丹薬を服用して崩御せり。
Because the world knows his throne was gained unjustly
彼の即位が正統でなかったとして
There is much debate about his merits and faults
世間で功過が大いに論じられたが
Finally honoring him as Emperor Xuanlie
最終的には「宣烈帝」と奉られしが
But among the people
民間では
They prefer another name
もう一つの別称を好みて曰く……